A new פרק, Perek, which is significantly of a, I would say,
easier, more accessible nature than what we have done before, which is
אותו ואת בנו. Oto Ve'et Beno. Now that we're done with שחטing
Shecht the animal and שחטing Shecht for טרפות Treifos and dealing with
bizarre cases of dangling limbs and fetuses, we get to other laws
relating to כשרות Kashrus or מצוות Mitzvos and prohibitions relating to eating
meat. So the first one is restrictions related to שחיטה Shechita and
the prohibition of שחטing Shecht an animal and its child on the
same day. אותו ואת בנו לא תשחטו ביום אחד. Oto Ve'et Beno
Lo Tishchatu Beyom Echad.
So let's take a look now as we move to the beginning
of the פרק, Perek, ע"ח ע"א, Ayin Chet Amud Aleph, the first
משנה. Mishnah. I'm sorry, okay, fine. So אותו ואת בנו, Oto Ve'et
Beno, an animal and its child. נוהג בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ,
Noheg Bein Ba'aretz Bein Bechutz La'aretz, that's the name of the prohibition
also, אותו ואת בנו. Oto Ve'et Beno. נוהג Noheg applies בין בארץ
בין בחוצה לארץ, Bein Ba'aretz Bein Bechutz La'aretz, whether in the land
of Israel or outside the land of Israel because it has nothing
to do with agriculture, so there is no reason why it should
not apply outside the land. Now this structure of does it apply
in the land of Israel or out? Does it apply by only
non-sanctified animals or even sacrifices? Does it apply only in the presence
of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or even when there's no בית
המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? Those are questions that are going to get asked
in the next few פרקים Perakim by a couple of different מצוות,
Mitzvos, by גיד הנשה, Gid HaNasheh, by the giving the ראשית הגז,
Reishis HaGez, the first of the shearings to the כהנים, Kohanim, giving
the first of the arm and the and the jaw and the
stomach, זרוע לחיים וקיבה Zero'a Lechayayim Vekivah and you know and the
and the stomach. So there's all these מצוות Mitzvos around שחיטה Shechita
and eating animals and all the משניות Mishnayos are going to go
through the questions of what is their scope. Do they apply sacrifices,
non-sacrifices, with the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, without the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, in the land of Israel, outside the land of Israel? Okay,
so that's the structure. Start it with our פרק. Perek. Let's take
a look again. אותו ואת בנו, Oto Ve'et Beno, this מצוה, Mitzvah,
נוהג בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ, Noheg Bein Ba'aretz Bein Bechutz La'aretz,
applies whether in the land of Israel or outside of the land
of Israel, בין בפני הבית בין שלא בפני הבית, Bein Bifnei HaBayit
Bein Shelo Bifnei HaBayit, whether there's a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or
not a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, which would make sense since it's
not related to the land of Israel, but okay. בחולין ובמוקדשין, BeChullin
UveMukdashin, whether in non-sanctified animals or sanctified animals. And now we're going
to go through all of the parameters, all of the permutations. It
is pretty clear, but we're going to go through the permutations to
look at the question of when you are חייב Chayav with different
types of, particularly between sanctified and non-sanctified,
what different types of עבירות Aveiros you may or may not perform
and whether it's in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or out of
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, we will see. Let's just go through
the structure and then take the questions. Okay, כיצד? Keitzad? חולין בחוץ
שניהם כשרים. Chullin Bachutz Sheneihem Kesherim. Now, כיצד, Keitzad, how is it
possible? השוחט אותו ואת בנו, Hashochet Oto Ve'et Beno, he שחטs Shecht
an animal and its child חולין בחוץ, Chullin Bachutz, they're both non-sanctified
and they're outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. שניהם כשרים, Sheneihem Kesherim,
both animals are kosher because although you transgressed a prohibition when you
שחט, Shecht, let me tell some parameters first of all about אותו
ואת בנו. Oto Ve'et Beno. It doesn't matter what order you do
it, whether you do the child first and then the mother or
the mother first and then the child. It doesn't matter if it's
the same person or not the same person, it's always the second
person who transgresses or the second שחיטה. Shechita. So if the child
or the mother has been שחטed Shecht on the same day that
the other generation has been שחטed, Shecht one who has effected
the second שחיטה Shechita and caused them both to be שחטed Shecht
on the same day is the one who transgresses. Now you might
not have thought that from the פסוק. Pasuk. You might have thought
you personally don't שחט Shecht both of them but לא תשחטו, Lo
Tishchatu, okay, right,
so you might be the cause of it. But nevertheless, yes, so
we say that it really means that it is the one who
does the second שחיטה. Shechita. The other thing by the way, as
I said mother and child, you'll notice that אותו Oto is in
the masculine. The גמרא Gemara will say that it applies by mother
and child, there's a debate whether it applies to father. So but
anyway again, it's the order doesn't matter, it goes by the person,
only the person who שחטs Shecht the second animal transgresses even if
he didn't שחט Shecht the first and the animal is kosher. You
yourself have transgressed a prohibition of not to שחט Shecht them both
at the same day, but the שחיטה Shechita is still a valid
שחיטה. Shechita. Okay, those are some of the parameters of אותו ואת
בנו. Oto Ve'et Beno. The משנה Mishnah particularly works focuses on the
aspect that the שחיטה Shechita is valid. Now that is going to
be contrasted to because notice we discussed the possibility of שחטing Shecht
קדשים Kodshim as well that you transgress. So we're now going to
discuss some scenarios of שחטing Shecht קדשים. Kodshim. Now by שחטing Shecht
קדשים, Kodshim, here are the ways in which that complicates things and
the משנה Mishnah is going to play with the issues. One is
if you שחט Shecht a קרבן Korban outside the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, you
transgress שחיטת חוץ, Shechitas Chutz, שחטing Shecht קדשים בחוץ Kodshim Bachutz and
you're חייב כרת. Chayav Kares. You'll also get lashes because pretty much
anything you get כרת Kares for you get lashes for. That's if
you שחטed Shecht outside. If you שחטed Shecht also outside the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it obviously doesn't work as a קרבן. Korban. So
number one is it's worse in that you're going to get כרת
kareis and you also get lashes and it won't be valid. In
addition, if ironically or whatever, if you are שוחט shochet a קרבן
korban outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash but you've שחט shechted the
mother that day or the child that day, so this is the
prohibition of אותו ואת בנו. oto ve'et beno. You're not חייב chayav
for שחיטה shechting a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Why? Since you can't bring this קרבן korban today in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash because you've... you're prohibited to שחט shecht this קרבן
korban today, therefore you do not transgress שחיטה shechting outside the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash which is only something that אל פתח אהל מועד
לא הביאו. el pesach ohel moed lo hevyo. Only something that could
have been brought today to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so
we're going to sort of play with all of these permutations of
שחיטה shechting חולין chullin in and out, קדשים kodshim in and out
and so on. But the basic rule is you're חייב chayav for
אותו ואת בנו oto ve'et beno if the second animal you שחט,
shecht, you can eat it. Those are the basic parameters there. And
by קדשים kodshim you're חייב chayav when you שחט shecht קדשים kodshim
out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you... oh, you can't eat
that obviously, קדשים kodshim שחט shechted outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
And also what do you call it? And you're not חייב chayav
if by קדשים kodshim שחיטה shechting out of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash if you שחט shechted the mother or child earlier that day
because then it means you're not allowed to שחט shecht so that
actually gets you off the hook. One final fact and then we're
going to play with all of these if this wasn't enough. If
you שחט shecht a חולין, chullin, a non-קדשים kodshim in the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, חולין בעזרה, chullin ba'azarah, that is prohibited but you
don't get lashes because there's not an explicit לאו. lav. But you're
not allowed to eat it. So a whole permutation of when can
you and can't you but for the very prohibition of אותו ואת
בנו oto ve'et beno you transgress you get lashes but you can
eat the animal. Now there were one or two questions before we
go ahead and read the משנה.
Mishnah. So is that why the משנה's Mishnah introducing the חוץ chutz
or קדשים kodshim and קדשים kodshim in בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and
not because there's something about these in different cases, I haven't seen
this until now.
Right. Well, I feel that everything we've done with מצוות mitzvos and
prohibitions we've done with שמיטה, sh'mittah, we've done with the prohibition of
טריפה, treifah, I suppose it's true, we could've discussed whether טריפה's treifah
חולין chullin and מוקדשין, mukdashin, that's true. But yeah, partly because we
are playing with this and partly because it is going to be
relevant by other things that relate to... these are prohibitions that are
not strictly about the כשרות kashrus of the animal. Similar to what
we're going to see like גיד הנשה gid hanasheh is and we'll
have a משנה Mishnah like that by גיד הנשה gid hanasheh but
you also have it by זרוע לחיים וקיבה zero'a lechayayim vehakeivah which
is a גז. gez. So these types of sort of מצוות mitzvos
that relate to animals, there's a whole structure about this, you know,
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash not בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, חולין, chullin, חולין
מוקדשין chullin mukdashin etc. It is possible here that it's specifically, you
know, like it's playing through these issues of חולין chullin and מוקדשין,
mukdashin, yes, that's right.
Right, one other thing, just practically, I mean you know I understand
it was probably easier to
enforce this shall we say when you had
each individual little guy had his own herd whatever, now that you
have these massive, how do they enforce this?
Right. So there's משניות Mishnayos that say that in general you know
you can assume that you don't have to worry that somebody else
שחט shechted the mother or child that day. You can just go
by law of averages and in general you know people things are
being mass-sold and mass-whatever, you know, you don't have to worry about
that except on particular days where it's assumed that everybody is going
to, anybody who's buying an animal today will שחט shecht today. Like
days which are right around certain ימים טובים Yomim Tovim and so
on. And there if you're the seller you have to inform somebody
that oh I sold the mother today so don't you're the second
buyer you know don't שחט shecht this if you're going to buy
this don't שחט shecht this today. So of course that only works
if the same seller sells both. If a different seller's selling them
yeah then you're sort of stuck.
So you're saying then that now that whoever it is, you know
the mass שוחט shochet is asking every supplier, you know, is the
mother...
Oh no no no that's not an issue because the... it's like
a crop cycle, you have a herd cycle that animals are only
שחט shecht when they reach a certain stage of development.
Well if that were true, right, right, I mean I guess today
in mass-produced meat that's true, yes that's true. Oh that's what you're
asking today. Yeah although sometimes like when you do veal you do
them younger and although... although veal is an interesting thing, exactly, interesting
thing I found out, veal is a byproduct of the dairy industry
because when you have cows, right, you want them to... if the
dairy cows give birth to females they can be more dairy cows.
If the dairy cows give birth to males what do you do
with them? So you don't want to you raise them as veal
because you don't want to spend great time raising them until the
full-grown and so anyway veal is a byproduct of that. So it's
pretty safe to say that if you're having veal you haven't also
eaten the mother's meat that day you haven't שחט shechted the mother
that day. Okay, you had a question Charlie? You answered it. Okay
fine, yes.
How far does he get into the offspring from אותו ואת בנו
oto ve'et beno to אותה ואת בנה?
otah ve'et benah? We'll see that in the... right, we'll see that
in the גמרא. Gemara. That's today's גמרא, Gemara, yes. Okay. Will you
have a problem שחט shecht say the grandchild of this? Uh, no.
Let's take a look. All right, all right, enough questions for now,
now let's get to the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, כיצד... keitzad... אותה ואת
בנו Otah Ve'et Beno to אותו ואת בנו. Oto Ve'et Beno. We'll
see that in right, right, we'll see that in the גמרא. Gemara.
That's in today's גמרא. Gemara. Yes. Okay. No problem substituting the grandchild
of this? No, let's take a look. All right. All right, all
right, enough questions for now. Now let's get to the משנה. Mishna.
Okay, כיצד? Keitzad? השוחט אותו ואת בנו. Hashochet Oto Ve'et Beno. So
you שוחט shochet an animal and its child. חולין בחוץ Chullin bachutz
if it's חולין Chullin outside the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, שניהם כשרים,
shneihem kesherim, they're both kosher because transgressing the prohibition does not make
the meat
forbidden. But the second person, notice even if it's not the same
person, whoever the second person is, he, the word סופג sofeg literally
means like he, he absorbs the lashes, but he is, he gets
the lashes. Okay, he's the one who transgresses. קדשים בחוץ, Kodshim bachutz,
let's say they're both sacrifices and they're out of the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash.
הראשון חייב כרת, Harishon chayav kares, the first person gets כרת, kares,
not for אותו ואת בנו, Oto Ve'et Beno, but for, but for
slaughtering a sacrifice outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
ושניהם פסולים, ushneihem psulim, both animals are invalid, not again because of
the prohibition of אותו ואת בנו, Oto Ve'et Beno, but because they're
sacrifices that have not been brought in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
So they're both, cannot be eaten. They're invalid as sacrifices and they
also can't be eaten.
ושניהם, v'shneihem, it's interesting. ושניהם v'shneihem in one case refers to the
animals and the other case refers to the people and both people
סופגים את הארבעים sofgin et ha'arba'im get the forty lashes. The first
guy gets the forty lashes for transgressing sacrifices out of the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. The second guy gets the forty lashes for transgressing
אותו ואת בנו. Oto Ve'et Beno. Why did the second guy not
also get the lashes for bringing, for slaughtering a קרבן korban out
of the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? Because by the time it got
around to his turn, this animal could not be, was not allowed
to be slaughtered this day because of אותו ואת בנו. Oto Ve'et
Beno. Since it could not be slaughtered, it's not fit for the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and since it's not fit for the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you don't transgress bringing a sacrifice outside if it
could not be brought inside. So therefore the second person only gets
lashes for אותו ואת בנו, Oto Ve'et Beno, not for a sacrifice
outside of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay. קדשים בפנים, Kodshim bifnim,
now, did I skip a line? It's so easy to skip a
line here. Okay, these are the, okay. חולין בפנים, Chullin bifnim, if
they were non-sanctified animals in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, שניהם פסולים,
shneihem psulim, they're both invalid because, not having to do with the
prohibition of אותו ואת בנו, Oto Ve'et Beno, but the principle is
that חולין Chullin slaughtered in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash cannot be
eaten. השני סופג את הארבעים Hasheni sofeg et ha'arba'im and only the
second one gets lashes. Why? Because of the transgression of אותו ואת
בנו. Oto Ve'et Beno. The transgression of slaughtering sacrifices in the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, excuse me, non-sacrifices, חולין Chullin in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash is learned from a positive מצוה mitzvah and there are
no lashes associated with it. Okay, so in חולין Chullin inside, you
can't eat them because of the problem of חולין Chullin inside, no
lashes for that, and again the second one gets lashes, אותו ואת
בנו. Oto Ve'et Beno. The theme about all of this is, the
second one is always going to get lashes for אותו ואת בנו.
Oto Ve'et Beno. Nothing gets the second guy off. Okay? But the,
whether it's קדשים, kodshim, whatever, the second guy is always going to
get lashes. The question is, can you eat it? What does the
first guy get? Can you eat the first one and so on.
Yes, what is it?
Does אותו ואת בנו Oto Ve'et Beno only apply if it's שחיטה
shechita though? Meaning like if the first one you,
you kill without שחיטה, shechita, you do not get, right, it's only
by שחיטה, shechita, correct. קדשים בפנים, Kodshim bifnim, הראשון כשר ופטור. Harishon
kasher upatur. Let's say they are קדשים kodshim in the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. So the first guy, it was a kosher sacrifice, right,
he slaughtered it in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and he's exempt.
It sort of goes without saying he's exempt, he actually did a
מצוה, mitzvah, he brought his קרבן korban in the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. That was the first guy. השני, Hasheni, the second guy, slaughtering
a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. The only problem
is he's got the right thing in the right spot, the only
problem is it's not the right time, okay? Because the mother was
slaughtered that day. So סופג את הארבעים, sofeg et ha'arba'im, he gets
lashes for אותו ואת בנו, Oto Ve'et Beno, ופסול, upasul, and the
קרבן korban is invalid. Okay, because if a קרבן, korban, and this
is an interesting note, as opposed to a non-קרבן, korban, just because
I transgress אותו ואת בנו Oto Ve'et Beno doesn't mean I can't
eat the meat. But by a קרבן, korban, there's the principle of
מחוסר זמן. mechussar zman. By a קרבן, korban, the principle is, right,
this appears in this תורה Torah by waiting till the eighth day.
Right? It says, you know, what's, what's the, וביום השמיני והלאה ירצה
לקרבן אשה לה'.
Uvayom hashmini
vahalah yeratzeh lekorban isheh laShem.
Only when it's eight days old can you bring it. From which
we learn, you know, the principle we, remember this, I don't know,
some people here might, well no, I think you're all roughly the
same age category anyway. Okay, second, we will sell no wine before
its time. You remember that ad? Yes, you remember. Anyway, we will
bring no קרבן korban before its time. So any קרבן korban that
is brought before its time is invalid. So since it cannot be
brought to be, it's not allowed to be slaughtered today because the
mother was slaughtered, that means it's not its time today, and since
it's not its time, it's invalid as a קרבן. korban. So that's
interesting. Does אותו ואת בנו, Oto Ve'et Beno, that prohibition, impact the
כשרות kashrus of the meat? So by a normal animal the answer
is no, you've transgressed and the meat is kosher. But by a
קרבן, korban, not really the כשרות kashrus but the validity it does
impact. Since you're not allowed to slaughter it today, it can't, it
cannot be brought as a קרבן. korban. So a קרבן korban slaughtered
not in the right time is invalid. And once it's invalid, obviously
then you can't eat from it. Okay. So when they're both קדשים
kodshim inside, the second guy in addition to being over on אותו
ואת בנו, Oto Ve'et Beno, also the קרבן korban is invalid and
cannot be eaten from. You have to bring another קרבן, korban, right.
Okay,
חולין וקדשים בחוץ. Chullin v'kodshim bachutz. Now as if that wasn't enough,
now that we're done with having both animals of the same of
the same type, now we're going to do mixed groups. Okay, you
have one animal is חולין chullin and one is קדשים. kodshim. That
order signifies, that's the order you're going to slaughter them. And they're
both outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so הראשון כשר ופטור.
harishon kasher u'patur. So the first animal is fine. It's a חולין
chullin slaughtered outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. It's כשר. kasher. You
didn't do anything wrong. Go ahead, eat the meat.
Wonderful. והשני, v'hasheini, the second one is a קדשים kodshim outside the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So certainly you're going to transgress אותו ואת
בנו, oso v'es b'no, right? That you never get out of by
the second one. Do you transgress קרבנות korbanos outside the בית המקדש?
Beis Hamikdash? No, since this is the prohibition of אותו ואת בנו
oso v'es b'no and since you're not allowed to bring it in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash because you can't slaughter it today, you
don't transgress for slaughtering it out of the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. והשני סופג את הארבעים, v'hasheini sofeig es ha'arbaim,
the second guy gets lashes but only one set. ופסול, u'pasul, and
it's invalid. It's invalid because it's a קרבן korban not brought in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But the חידוש chiddush of this is,
although here the חידוש chiddush is less, is more implicit, is it's
only one set of lashes and not two. He doesn't get כרת.
kares. The חידוש chiddush is that you slaughtered it out of the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you do not transgress for קדשים בחוץ kodshim
bachutz because since it was not allowed to be slaughtered today, it
couldn't have been even a valid קרבן korban in the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash.
Yes, so they're getting off on a technicality before they get to
something like
as the שאל shaal asked that question. Correct. Yes, right. Okay, now,
okay, קדשים וחולין בחוץ. kodshim v'chullin bachutz. Same thing except you reversed
the order. You start with your קרבן korban outside and then you're
going to do your non-קרבן korban outside. Now you're in big trouble
because you're starting with your קרבן korban outside. That's קדשים בחוץ. kodshim
bachutz. Okay, הראשון חייב כרת. harishon chayav kares.
The first guy gets כרת kares and lashes. ופסול, u'pasul, and it's
invalid. It's a קרבן שחטו korban shachato out of the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. והשני, v'hasheini, the second guy כשר. kasher. The meat is
כשר kasher because again your transgression does not prevent normal חולין chullin
from being valid. So you slaughtered it, you transgressed, but it's still
כשר. kasher. It's a non-sanctified animal. ושניהם סופגים את הארבעים. u'shneihem sofgeem
es ha'arbaim. They both get lashes. The first guy for transgressing קדשים
בחוץ kodshim bachutz and the second guy for
transgressing אותו ואת בנו. oso v'es b'no. חולין וקדשים בפנים. chullin v'kodshim
bifnim.
Now again a mixed group, but they're both being done in the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. You start with your חולין chullin and then
your קרבן korban in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So let's see,
let's not read inside. Let's see if by now we can figure
this out. Okay, see how much you've been paying attention. So חולין,
chullin, a קרבן korban in. So the חולין chullin in the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, do you get lashes?
You said you don't do it.
You don't get lashes for חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. Okay, can you
eat the meat? No, no, because חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah you don't
eat the meat. Okay, the next comes the guy who's bringing the
קרבן korban in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, does he get
lashes for אותו ואת בנו? oso v'es b'no? Yes. Yes. Okay, is
the קרבן כשר? korban kasher? No. Okay, very good. So let's take
a look. All right, so חולין וקדשים בפנים, chullin v'kodshim bifnim, שניהם
פסולים, shneihem pesulim, both are invalid. One for חולין בעזרה, chullin ba'azarah,
the other because it is a קרבן korban brought before its time.
והשני סופג את הארבעים, v'hasheini sofeig es ha'arbaim, only the second guy
gets lashes because of אותו ואת בנו. oso v'es b'no. קדשים וחולין
בפנים, kodshim v'chullin bifnim, same thing in the reverse order.
But why isn't it כשר kasher though, the second one?
Because a קרבן korban that is not a כשר קרבן kasher korban
is not valid as a קרבן, korban, cannot be eaten as the
meat.
I thought it was that it was slaughtered the same day, that's
why it's not כשר. kasher.
No, it's not because it was slaughtered the same day. I mean,
that's indirectly why. Any
קרבן korban that's slaughtered and doesn't work as a קרבן, korban, the
fact that it's sanctified means that it can't be eaten unless it
works as a כשר קרבן. kasher korban.
Why didn't it work as a קרבן? korban?
Oh, that is because of אותו ואת בנו oso v'es b'no and
it was not considered its time yet. Correct. Okay, so now we
have the same mixed group but the reverse order.
Where was? קדשים וחולין בפנים.
kodshim
v'chullin bifnim.
Okay, now I totally lost my place. קדשים וחולין בפנים. kodshim v'chullin
bifnim. Okay, so let's see if we can figure this out again.
So קדשים וחולין בפנים. kodshim v'chullin bifnim. The first one a קרבן
korban in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. What's the story? כשר, kasher,
very good. Wonderful, you did your מצוה. mitzvah. Good. The second guy
חולין בעזרה, chullin ba'azarah, אותו ואת בנו, oso v'es b'no,
can it be eaten? No, no, well yes, אותו ואת בנו oso
v'es b'no and חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. Does he get two lashes?
No, you only get lashes for you don't get lashes for חולין
בעזרה, chullin ba'azarah, only for אותו ואת בנו. oso v'es b'no. Can
it be eaten? No, חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah can't be eaten. Okay,
so let's take a look. קדשים וחולין בפנים, kodshim v'chullin bifnim, הראשון
כשר ופטור, harishon kasher u'patur, the first one is כשר kasher and
you're exempt, obviously you're exempt, you did the right thing. והשני סופג
את הארבעים, v'hasheini sofeig es ha'arbaim, the second guy gets one set
of lashes for אותו ואת בנו. oso v'es b'no. ופסול, u'pasul, but
the meat cannot be eaten because of the problem of חולין בעזרה.
chullin ba'azarah.
Now, now that we did a mixed group, now we're going to
do one genre but in two different places. Hushy's still having fun.
חולין בחוץ ובפנים. chullin bachutz u'bifnim. So both animals are חולין, chullin,
one was outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and the other was
inside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so הראשון כשר ופטור, harishon
kasher u'patur, the חולין chullin outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is
of course fine. והשני, v'hasheini, the second guy is חולין בעזרה. chullin
ba'azarah. So what's the דין din of חולין בעזרה? chulin ba'azarah? No
lashes, can't be eaten, but he gets lashes for אותו ואת בנו.
oso ve'es bino. סופג ארבעים, soveig arbayim, he gets lashes, ופסול, upasul,
the meat can't be eaten because of חולין בעזרה. chulin ba'azarah.
קדשים בחוץ ובפנים, Kodashim bachutz uvifnim, both animals are קדשים, kodashim, one
outside and one inside. So the קדשים kodashim outside, כרת, kares, lashes,
don't eat it, הראשון חייב כרת. harishon chayav kares. Now how about
by the time you get to the one inside, okay? A קרבן
korban in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. פסול Pasul קרבן korban because
it's אותו ואת בנו, oso ve'es bino, so you can't bring it
today, okay? And you get lashes for אותו ואת בנו, oso ve'es
bino, and you can't eat it because it's
a פסול pasul קרבן, korban, but it doesn't get כרת.
kares. Right. שניהם סופקין את הארבעים, Sheneihem sofkin es ha'arbayim, they both
get lashes, one for קדשים בחוץ, kodashim bachutz, the other for אותו
ואת בנו, oso ve'es bino, ושניהם פסולים, usheneihem psulim, both are invalid
because they are invalid קרבנות korbanos and therefore invalid קרבנות korbanos cannot
be eaten. Now we have the same thing, one genre in two
different places, but we're reversing the order. Starting in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. חולין בפנים ובחוץ, Chulin bifnim uvachutz, so
you have חולין, chulin, you started in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and then you're going out of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So
the first one is חולין בעזרה, chulin ba'azarah, no lashes, can't be
eaten.
הראשון פסול, Harishon pasul, it can't be eaten, ופטור, upatur, you're exempt
from lashes. והשני, Vahashayni, the second thing, חולין chulin out of the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, fine, except that it's אותו ואת בנו. oso
ve'es bino. השני סופג את הארבעים, Hashayni soveig es ha'arbayim, gets lashes,
וכשר, vekasher, but the meat can be eaten because it's חולין chulin
meat slaughtered outside the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash.
כרת Kares is only for קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. So this was the other one.
This was חולין. chulin.
This was before that though, same thing, it was inside and he
doesn't get כרת kares because it was inside.
Right, right. And now we're going to do קדשים בפנים ובחוץ, kodashim
bifnim uvachutz, קרבן korban inside and then outside. הראשון כשר, Harishon kasher,
the first is a קרבן korban inside, wonderful, ופטור, upatur, obviously you're
exempt. והשני, Vahashayni, the second guy, סופג את הארבעים, soveig es ha'arbayim,
gets lashes for אותו ואת בנו, oso ve'es bino, ופסול, upasul, the
meat can't be eaten because it's a קרבן korban outside the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but the one thing that you don't get is
כרת kares because of the prohibition of אותו ואת בנו, oso ve'es
bino, it wasn't its time to be brought as a קרבן. korban.
But you get lashes and כרת kares though?
Well, it means lashes or כרת. kares. If you get lashes, you're
exempt from כרת. kares. Okay, so the upshot of all this is
that A, a different, you don't need to be the same person
to get, I mean as far as we're concerned of אותו ואת
בנו, oso ve'es bino, you don't need to be the same person
to get אותו ואת בנו, oso ve'es bino, could be a different
person, the second person is the one that transgresses. The transgression does
not invalidate the meat. The difference is by a קרבן, korban, the
prohibition of אותו ואת בנו oso ve'es bino invalidates the קרבן korban
and therefore indirectly invalidates the meat because if it's not the time
to be brought as a קרבן, korban, it's not a כשר kasher
קרבן. korban. Okay, now we turn to, that was, I mean, you
know, it was just a lot of things to go through, but
conceptually it was not complicated. And the גמרא Gemara will be pretty
straightforward as well.
It's really interesting, so you know I may not know you at
all, you brought your קרבן korban and you're fine and then I'm
bringing my חולין chulin and like and I'm getting lashes.
Unless you're... yeah, if you do it intentionally you get lashes, if
you do it with negligence you did a prohibition with negligence, if
you were totally unwitting and no reason to know, then you're an
אונס. oness. But you are right that it's a pretty funny system
that set up in a way that even if as a normal
consumer I don't have to be concerned about it, you know, because
what's the likelihood somebody else שחט shachted the mother today, that there'll
be a lot of transgressions being done באונס. be'oness. You know, it
is a pretty funny system, that is true. Okay, let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, מנין לאותו ואת
בנו שנוהג במוקדשים? Minayin le'oso ve'es bino shenoheig bemukdashim? How do we
know that it applies even to קרבנות? korbanos? תוספות Tosafos has a
whole discussion why would I have thought otherwise, but okay, we don't
worry about that. How do I know? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, because
the שור או כשב או עז shor o chesev o ez right
before אותו ואת בנו oso ve'es bino is this idea of having
to wait eight days for a קרבן. korban. It says שור או
כשב או עז כי יולד והיה שבעת ימים תחת אמו, Shor o
chesev o ez ki yivaled vehaya shivas yamim tachas imo, seven days
with its mother, וביום השמיני והלאה ירצה לקרבן אשה לה׳. ubayom hashmini
vahala yeiratzeh lekorban isheh laShem. And then it says ושור או שה
אותו ואת בנו לא תשחטו ביום אחד. Veshor o seh oso ve'es
bino lo tishchatu beyom echad. So right after saying wait eight days
to bring something as a קרבן, korban, it says don't slaughter a
sheep or a cow and it and its child on the same
day. So first of all, one thing that that juxtaposition might indicate
is the idea that אותו ואת בנו oso ve'es bino makes it
considered like the משנה Mishnah said מחוסר זמן, mechusar zman, that if
you're not allowed to slaughter on the same day, it's like being
less than eight days old and is invalid as a קרבן. korban.
That could be suggested by that juxtaposition. But what the גמרא Gemara
is going to suggest by the juxtaposition is that the prohibition applies
even to קרבנות. korbanos. And then the next question is going to
be maybe it applies only to קרבנות, korbanos, like the eight day
issue applies only to קרבנות. korbanos. So let's see that in the
גמרא. Gemara. שור או כשב או עז כי יולד, Shor o chesev
o ez ki yivaled, וכתיב בתריה uchsiv basrei and then it says
ושור או שה אותו ואת בנו לא תשחטו ביום אחד. Veshor o
seh oso ve'es bino lo tishchatu beyom echad. So since the previous
one was about קרבנות, korbanos, right, לימד על אותו ואת בנו, limed
al oso ve'es bino, the juxtaposition teaches that even the prohibition of
אותו ואת בנו oso ve'es bino שנוהג במוקדשין, shenoheig bemukdashin, it applies
by קרבנות. korbanos. So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא במוקדשין אין בחולין
לא, Ve'eima bemukdashin in bechulin lo, maybe just by קרבנות, korbanos, which
is reasonable, right, since right before it was speaking about what are
the parameters of bringing a קרבן. korban. שור הפסיק הענין. Shor hifsik
ha'inyan. No, because then it would have just said ולא תשחטו ביום
אחד v'lo tishchatu b'yom echad or ואותו ואת בנו לא תשחטו ביום
אחד. v'oto v'et bno lo tishchatu b'yom echad. The fact that it
once again repeats the animals ושור או שה v'shor o seh means
now we're on a new topic. We're not limiting ourselves to the
previous context of talking just about קורבנות. korbanot. So it also relates
to קורבנות korbanot but it also relates to non-קורבנות, korbanot, any ox
or sheep, don't שחט shecht it and the child on the same
day. ואימא בחולין אין במוקדשים לא, ve'eima be'chullin in be'mukdashim lo, so
if we're on a new topic then say only by non-קורבנות korbanot
and it does not apply to קורבנות. korbanot. How do you have
it both ways? גמרא Gemara says כתיב ושור, ketiv v'shor, it says
and as for an ox, ו מוסיף על ענין ראשון, vav mosif
al inyan rishon, so that connects it. So on the one hand
because of the ו vav it relates also to קורבנות, korbanot, on
the other hand because it sort of started the sentence new and
didn't continue from the previous פסוק pasuk as it were that it
also applies... is not limited to קורבנות korbanot and applies to non-קורבנות
korbanot as well. Let's do it again. Nice. Charlie had a question.
So this brings up the issue does אותו ואת בנו oto v'et
bno apply to an animal that's less than eight days old?
Oh, that's an interesting question but certainly for, yeah, because first of
all that less than eight days is irrelevant for a non-קורבן. korban.
Would it apply for a קורבן korban less than eight days? I
don't see why not.
You're attacking it on the other...
Right, we've been saying the prohibition of אותו ואת בנו oto v'et
bno affects the validity of a קורבן. korban. You're saying let's say
it's a פסול pasul קורבן, korban, are you חייב chayav for אותו
ואת בנו? oto v'et bno? Well, that gets to the question which
we will get to later which is whether שחיטה שאינה ראויה שמה
שחיטה, shechitah she'einah re'uyah shemah shechitah, whether a שחיטה shechitah that makes
something not kosher meat is it still considered to be an act
of שחיטה shechitah for these prohibitions. Now our משנה mishna assumes the
answer to that is yes because our משנה mishna has you שוחט
shechting קדשים בחוץ kodshim bachutz which is שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechitah she'einah
re'uyah, it's פסול pasul as a קורבן korban and you're חייב chayav
for אותו ואת בנו. oto v'et bno. So I don't see why
שוחט shechting a קורבן korban less than eight days old should be
any different than שוחט shechting a קורבן korban outside the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and you should still presumably be חייב chayav for אותו
ואת בנו. oto v'et bno. Okay. So now we've decided yes.
And I also want to say even
afterwards it goes right back to
קורבנות. korbanot. That's true.
Okay. They could have done that. Okay. So anyway now we know
that it applies whether קורבן korban or non-קורבן korban and now let's
keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא קדשים כלאים לא
אף אותו ואת בנו כלאים לא, ve'eima kodshim kilayim lo af oto
v'et bno kilayim lo, maybe the juxtaposition should tell us something more.
The same way a קורבנות korbanot do not work if they are
a crossbreed which רש''י Rashi says means a sheep mates with a
goat. Does that... can that happen? Can they give birth? Okay. Why
is it that you can crossbreed a horse and a donkey but
you can't breed a sheep and a goat?
They're very closely related.
Really? It would seem like a sheep and a goat are pretty
closely related.
They get offspring but they're sterile.
Well right, that's what a mule is. Right. Anyway, so if somehow
you manage to crossbreed, it would not be good as a
קורבן korban because the קורבן korban has to be either a sheep
or a goat or a cow, not something in the middle. So
maybe I should say that you don't transgress for אותו ואת בנו
oto v'et bno by a crossbreed. Maybe that's true, right? The תורה
Torah just says שור או שה. shor o seh. And by the
way although it's not mentioned in this משנה, mishna, you know what
you don't transgress for? A חיה. chayah. If you שוחט shecht a
deer and its offspring on the same day, you don't transgress. So
שור או שה shor o seh is not generic. It really means
that it has to be a בהמה, behemah, a שור shor or
שה. seh. So maybe it should be... so interestingly it does apply
to a כלאים, kilayim, some type of a crossbreed, but says maybe
it shouldn't based on the juxtaposition. Right. Right, because the chicken is
not... it's through an egg and this is a live offspring. Okay.
So anyway let's take a look.
But we take for granted it does apply to כלאים. kilayim. אף
אותו ואת בנו כלאים לא. af oto v'et bno kilayim lo. But
based on the juxtaposition maybe I should say it does not apply
to כלאים. kilayim. אלמה תניא, alama tanya, why do we teach in
a ברייתא, braisa, אותו ואת בנו נוהג בכלאים, oto v'et bno noheg
be'kilayim, it applies to כלאים kilayim ובכוי. u've'koy. Now
the כוי koy is one of those animals that is indeterminate whether
it is a חיה chayah or a בהמה. behemah. So although it
doesn't apply by a חיה, chayah, it does apply to a כוי.
koy. Now does it apply to a כוי koy by ספק, safek,
as a ספק, safek, because maybe it's a בהמה? behemah? Anyway we'll
worry about that later. But for now what interests us is that
it applies to כלאים kilayim and in that way it is not
like a קורבן. korban. ועוד, ve'od, and here's another reason why we
should argue it does not apply to כלאים. kilayim. שה כתיב, seh
ketiv, it says, you know, שור או שה, shor o seh, a
sheep. ואמר רבא, ve'amar Rava, and רבא Rava has said in a
different context, זה בני אב, zeh bni av, this from this we
learn a basic paradigm. כל מקום שנאמר שה אינו אלא להוציא את
הכלאים. kol makom shene'emar seh eino ela lehoti es hakilayim. שה seh
means something that is not a crossbreed. How does he get it
from? רש''י Rashi says because the תורה Torah says שה כשבים ושה
עזים. seh chesavim v'seh izim. Mentions explicitly a שה seh of sheep
or שה seh of goats, which indicates that it's one or the
other, not some type of a crossbreed. So שה seh means something
that is not a crossbreed. So we have two reasons to say
non-crossbreed by אותו ואת בנו. oto v'et bno. So why do we
include
them? אמר קרא או לרבות את הכלאים, amar kra o lerabbot es
hakilayim, because it says ושור או. v'shor o. או, o, it could
have said ושור ושה, veshor veseh, או o means like it's somehow
seen as or, the or word is always a more inclusive word,
you know, than an and word, this or this or that, so
somehow או o includes even something that is between a, you know,
something that is a crossbreed, that is between the two. So
the גמרא... Gmara... או לרבות לכלאים. o l'rabbos l'kilayim. גמרא Gmara says
one minute, האי או מיבעי ליה לחלק. hai o miba'ei lei l'chaleik.
No, no, no, you can't say או o is extra because and
means something very different than or. If you said
ושור ושה, אותו ואת בנו, veshor veseh oso ves bno. maybe you
would only transgress if you שחט shechted an ox, a sheep, and
their children all at the same time, אותו ואת בנו.
oso ves bno, All
right, so we'll take, the גמרא Gmara will talk about that. You
need it to לחלק, l'chaleik, to say this or that. דסלקא דעתך
אמינא, d'salka da'atach amina, if it would have just said a ו,
vav, I would have thought עד דשחיט שור ובנו ושה ובנו, ad
d'shachit shor u'vno v'seh u'vno, you would need to do
both an ox and its child and a sheep and its child.
גמרא Gmara says לא מחייב, lo m'chayev, until you did that you
would not be חייב. chayiv. קא משמע לן לחלק, kamashmalan l'chaleik, and
so therefore you need the או o to say it's one or
the other, not both. So גמרא Gmara says no, no, no, מבנו
נפקא, mi'bno nafkuh, which is what Michael was saying, because even if
you didn't have the או, o, it would have said שור ושה
אותו ואת בנו, shor veseh oso ves bno, it didn't say אותם
ואת בנם, osam ves bnam, it said אותו ואת בנו, oso ves
bno. so that's in the singular, so you would have known from
that that we mean one or the other, not both, and therefore
the או o is still extra. גמרא Gmara says one minute, דהא
מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, d'ha miba'ei lei l'chid'tanya, you
still need the או o for what we taught in the ברייתא.
Baraita. Here's what the
ברייתא Baraita says: אילו נאמר שור ושה ובנו, ilu ne'emar shor veseh
u'vno, an ox and a sheep and its singular
child, הייתי אומר עד שישחוט שור ושה ובנו, hayiti omer ad she'yishchot
shor veseh u'vno, at least you need three animals, an ox, a
sheep, and at least one of their child, right? You wouldn't need
both of their children because as Michael says it doesn't say בנם,
bnam, but you would have needed all three animals, an ox, a
sheep, and one child. תלמוד לומר שור או שה אותו ואת בנו.
Talmud lomar shor o seh oso ves bno. So the או o
comes to tell you no, it's either you know one or the
other, it's not three, it's two, an ox and its child or
a sheep and its child. So you see you still need the
word או o to divide, otherwise even with the word בנו bno
I would have said three. גמרא Gmara says מאי לאו מאו נפקא,
mai lav mei'O nafkuh, isn't it the או o that serves that
function of telling you one or the other, not some combination? The
גמרא Gmara says no, לא מאותו, lo mei'oto, from the word of
אותו, oto, because here's the point. When the... I would have thought
three, it took out two words, it said had the verse said
ושור ושה ובנו, veshor veseh u'vno, I would have said three animals,
right? But what the actual verse does say is it adds two
other words to that phrase to clarify. It says ושור או שה,
veshor o seh, and then it doesn't just say ובנו, u'vno, it
says אותו ואת בנו. oso ves bno, So what the גמרא Gmara
is saying is the word או o is extra, I'll prove it
to you. Here's how the verse could have been
written: ושור ושה veshor veseh, אותו ואת בנו. oso ves bno. If
the end of the verse had said אותו ואת בנו oso ves
bno in singular, it singular and its child, then even though it
would have started by ושור ושה, veshor veseh, it obviously would have
meant an ox or a sheep, right? Because it couldn't have meant
an ox and a sheep because then it wouldn't have been able
to end אותו ואת בנו, oso ves bno, it would have had
to say אותם ואת בנו osam ves bno or ואת בנם. ves
bnam. So אותו ואת בנו oso ves bno makes it clear we're
talking about one animal and one child. So therefore the או o
is extra in the beginning of the verse and that או o
is coming to tell me even a כלאים, kilayim, crossbreed. Okay, phew,
now we think we're done, but the גמרא Gmara is still not
done, let's take a look.
גמרא Gmara says הניחא לרבנן דמיותר ליה אותו, hani nicha l'rabbanan d'miyatar
lei oso, that's good for the רבנן Rabbanan that have the
word אותו oso as extra, אלא לחנניה דלא מיותר ליה אותו לחלק
מנא ליה? ela l'Chananya d'lo miyatar lei oso l'chaleik minalei? חנניה Chananya
does not have the word אותו oso as extra, how does he
know to separate the two? Now, why does חנניה, Chananya, we're going
to see at the bottom of the דף, daf, why does חנניה
Chananya not have the word אותו oso as extra? Because he uses
the word אותו oso to tell you we're talking even about the
father, not only the mother and the child, even the father and
the child. So since אותו oso is extra and it's in the
male, the masculine, it means even the father and the child. So
that's what he gets out of the word אותו. oso. So for
him, where do we know to split the פסוק pasuk and say
it means the sheep or ox, not them combined? Because until now
we've been assuming the only way we know not them combined is
the word אותו. oso. But חנניה Chananya uses the word אותו oso
for something else. So where does he know to divide it if
we don't have the
word או? o? So the גמרא Gmara says לחלק לא צריך קרא,
l'chaleik lo tzarich k'ra, no, he'll tell you you don't need a
separate special word to לחלק, l'chaleik, to divide the two, to say
that it means or. דסבר ליה כרבי יונתן, d'savar lei k'Rabbi Yonasan,
and he'll hold like רבי יונתן, Rabbi Yonasan, and now we're going
to see there's a general debate when the תורה Torah uses the
word ו, vav, am I entitled to say it means or, or
do I need to assume it means and unless I have evidence
otherwise? Okay? דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא: Baraita:
איש איש אשר יקלל את אביו ואת אמו, ish ish asher yikalel
es aviv v'es imo, if a person curses literally his mother, his
father and his mother, not or his mother, and his mother. אין
לי אלא אביו ואמו, ein li ela aviv v'imo, I only know
if a person curses both his father and mother.
אביו שלא אמו aviv shelo imo A father without his mother, a
mother without the father, מנין, minayin, how do I know you transgress,
how do I know to read the verse as an or essentially?
תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, the next verse says אביב ואמו קלל, aviv
ve'immo killel, his father and mother he has cursed. So again it
says both, but the difference is what word is juxtaposed to the
word קלל, killel, curse? In the first verse, it is אשר יקלל
את אביו, asher yekallel et aviv, so the word father is
juxtaposed to יקלל, yekallel, to curse. Here it is אביב ואמו קלל.
aviv ve'immo killel. The word mother is juxtaposed. So that tells you
whether the curse is to his father or his mother, either way
you transgress. אביו קלל אמו קלל, aviv killel immo killel, whether you
curse the father or the mother, either way, because you have an
extra verse, it tells you it means either, not both. דברי רבי
יאשיה. divrei Rabbi Yoshiya. That is what Rabbi Yoshiya says. So Rabbi
Yoshiya said without the extra verse, I would have assumed that a
ו vav means and and not or, and you need a verse
to teach me that it means or. רבי יונתן אומר, Rabbi Yonatan
omer, Rabbi Yonatan says no. משמע שניהם כאחד ומשמע אחד בפני עצמו.
mashma sheneihem ke'echad umashma echad bifnei atzmo.
Any ו vav can be read to mean and, both together, or
it could mean one by itself, or. A ו vav can be
interpreted to be or, and we will interpret it that way. עד
שיפרוט לך הכתוב יחדיו, ad sheyifrot lecha hakatuv yachdav, until the verse
says together. What verse does the verse say together?
לא תחרוש בשור ובחמור
יחדיו.
lo tacharosh beshor
uvachamor yachdav.
So when it says together, then you know it means and. Otherwise,
if it just said לא תחרוש בשור ובחמור, lo tacharosh beshor uvachamor,
you would have said you can never plow with an ox or
with a donkey. But that would have been a little difficult. Okay,
anyway, all right, so here is the basic debate. Does ו vav
mean and and it only means and unless you have an explicit
indication otherwise, or can I interpret it as or? So basically, let's
get back to what the purpose of this whole discussion was. The
purpose of this whole discussion, very long discussion, was to figure out
how we know that אותו ואת בנו oso ve'es bno applies to
כלאים kilayim across breeds. And we said by the extra word או,
o,
A or B, the or was extra. Because what? The or is
extra, you need it to tell me it means A or B.
So he says no no, that we get from the word אותו
ואת בנו. oso ve'es bno. What do you do with חנניה Chananya
that uses אותו oso for something else? Oh, he would assume that
also that you don't need the word or. He would assume like
this רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan we just said that we always even
with a ו vav assume
a
ו vav means or. We don't have to read it as and.
Or because at least the word of אותו. oso. That tells you
A or B. So since the word או o is extra, it
allows us to teach this principle of כלאים kilayim of a crossbreed.
Okay, but in the process we have introduced the issue of the
חכמים chachamim and חנניה, Chananya, and this gets us to focus on
the parameters of אותו ואת בנו. oso ve'es bno. So let's take
a look now at that.
מאי חנניה מאי רבנן? mai Chananya mai rabanan? What is the debate
of the Rabbis and
Chananya? דתניא, detanya, it taught in a ברייתא. braisa. אותו ואת בנו
נוהג בנקבות ואינו נוהג בזכרים. oso ve'es bno noheg binkevos ve'eino noheg
bizecharim. It applies to mothers and not to fathers, which is quite
ironic since it is in the masculine. So we will see why.
חנניה אומר, Chananya omer, Chananya says, נוהג בין בזכרים בין בנקבות. noheg
bein bizecharim bein binkevos. It applies even if, whether mothers or fathers.
Now we are just talking, I am saying specifically mothers or fathers
because there
is no debate that it doesn't, that the sex of the child
does not matter. Although it says בנו, bno, not בתו bito or
whatever, right, but there is an assumption that you know, that the
masculine in the Hebrew is also the generic, so בנו bno means
child. So there was never a debate about the child, the debate
is about the mother. Okay, or the parent. Is the parent only
the mother or even the mother and the father? Again, it is
quite ironic because the whole verse is in the masculine, but everybody
agrees it is the mother, what is being debated is the father.
Now it might have to do a little bit with indications in
the verse, but what it really I think has more to do
or at least equal to do with this principle that the גמרא
Gemara introduces, which is called חוששין לזרע האב. choseshin lezera ha'av. Are
you concerned about the seed of the father? And that concerned means
concerned in two ways. Number one is do we even know who
the father is? Okay, that the תורה Torah should reasonably tell us
something about the father that you know, is that assumed that something
that we should or do know about, especially in the animal world?
And number two is even if we do know who the father
is, to what degree is there a sense
of a relationship
between the father and the child? Now again, this is a little
ironic because you know, in הלכה, halacha, of course, the primary relationship
is father and child, even though the mother is the one that
gives birth, you know, it is a, you know, it very much
works you know in terms
of of defining descendants based on father for people. I know. Based
on father and child. Why would it be the opposite by animals?
And it seems to be, and this is also a thing that
the גמרא Gemara has when it comes to slaves, and assumes that
the you know, the children are not מיוחס meyuchas after their father
by slaves. It seems to be that the גמרא Gemara recognizes that
at a biological level, it is about you know, mothers and children,
the connection is obviously much more intense, right? I mean the mother
carries for nine months and gives birth and so on.
it was a one-minute act and then the relationship really, the biological
relationship is much more intense. So that the father-child relationship is much
more a function of a societal and social structure, right? That recognizes
the father's role and that maybe even gives that primacy over the
relationship over the biological relationship over the mother. So that's not true
by animals, right? Those you don't have that social structure of
fatherhood, and slaves as well, as we know, the whole idea of
family structure is very, you know, it's not really present amongst slaves.
So anyway,
or often not the case. So that really seems why the גמרא
Gemara takes for, you know, there's a question of חוששים לזרע האב.
chosheshim l'zera ha-av. And it's also the very phrase of לזרע האב,
l'zera ha-av, like that's his one contribution, he gave the seed and
then he left. You know, so does that have any continued role
in terms of the identity, in terms of relating to the offspring
when you're not dealing in a human societal structure where fatherhood, you
know, and hus- you know, really matters? You had a comment?
There are a few mammals who do have the family social structure
but none of them are kosher.
That's interesting. Also, isn't it mostly, who, and most of the time
anyway, even in those with the social structure, it's still the mother
that much more is with the children, right?
Or not the case?
Well, I'm thinking of lions, maybe not. Lions, the mother go out
and hunt and the kids stay behind. Lions,
wolves, yeah.
There's only one male that will generally mate.
But who stays more with the family, as it were?
It's more debatable. Okay, fine.
Okay, but anyway, as a general rule, when you're looking at animals
and you're looking at the biological reality, the father is much less
of a significant factor.
But birds... birds actually often... that's interesting. The majority of bird species...
that's interesting.
Yes, birds do. I'm totally, always totally confused when the rabbis choose
to zero in on
the masculine language like
למדתם את בניכם, limadetem et bneichem,
and there are times relating to people like כי יגח שור איש,
ki yigach shor ish, and there the rabbis say it's not only
a שור shor belonging to men, it's belonging to a אישה ishah
also. So they're very loose with when they choose to zero in
on masculine and when
they just ignore...
I agree. I know. Well, that's why I tried to give you
what I thought was informing the issue here, was the, that it
was really not the language, but it was starting with the concept
of חוששים לזרע האב. chosheshim l'zera ha-av. How relevant is the idea
of being a father in the animal world? So to think that
the Torah recognizes a relationship between father and offspring amongst animals is
something that they're much more skeptical about and inclines them to assume
that the verse is referring to the mother.
I mean, actually, sometimes when you have a bull, you'll have one
bull for the entire site, so you do know who the father
is.
But I'm just saying
it's
not just a question of knowledge, it's a question of how relevant
it is, you know. The father, fine, inseminates the mother and he
leaves, you know. They actually have that, right? They have stud farms
or whatever for bulls and for, so you go, you do the
one act and you leave. How much does that create a relationship?
So that is, I think, what the assumptions that are being brought
in here that are inclining the גמרא Gemara to assume that it
does not refer to the father.
I'm not saying צער בעלי חיים.
tza'ar ba'alei chayim. I'm not saying צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim.
But
why does that matter? Because whatever the, whatever the reason is for
אותו ואת בנו, oto v'et bno, we can discuss that later, it
certainly is a function of seeing them as some connected family unit,
right? And therefore, whether it is the suffering that the parent will
suffer or the child will suffer, whether it is what the רמב"ן
Ramban says that it has nothing to do with the suffering of
the animals, it has to do with a callousness that you breed
in yourself that you're wiping out a whole family, but whatever it
is, it requires at the foundation that these are seen as some
type of a family. That makes a lot more sense when you're
dealing with the biological reality of being a mother than when you're
dealing with the father that was there for ten seconds and never
really connected as a family. That's why I think...
why birds
though?
What? Oh alright, that's a question, exactly. The parameters... yes, we have
two more quick questions and then we're getting to the end of
the דף. daf. What? שילוח הקן? shiluach haken? Yes, שילוח הקן, shiluach
haken,
very good. So שילוח הקן shiluach haken we're going to see at
the end of the דף, daf, there it is, everybody agrees it's
the mother because it says האם רובצת על הבנים ha'em rovetzet al
habanim and it says אם em more than once. So everybody agrees
that that is mother, yes.
First I was going to say, you know, how that informs this
debate, but also that then if it is the mother, why does
it go so specifically to say אותו? oto?
You know,
in other words... right, אותו? oto? Right. That's a good question. Alright,
let's read the גמרא. Gemara. I don't have an answer. Let's read
the גמרא. Gemara.
I got it. I got it. Let's read the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
מאי חנניה מאי רבנן? mai Chananya mai rabbanan? דתניא, de-tanya, we're talking
about a ברייתא. braisa. אותו ואת בנו oto ve-et beno דכוותה שאינו
אלא בנקבה. de-chvata she-eino ella bi-nekevah. חנניה אומר נוהג בין בזכר בין
בנקבה. Chananya omer noheg ben bi-zachar ben bi-nekevah.
Okay, so the Rabbis say only mothers and חנניה Chananya says mothers
and fathers. מאי טעמא דרבנן? mai taama de-rabbanan? What's the reason of
the Rabbis? דתניא. de-tanya. יכול יהיה אותו ואת בנו נוהג בין בזכר
בין בנקבה, yakhol yehei oto ve-et beno noheg ben bi-zachar ben bi-nekevah,
maybe it would apply to fathers and mothers. ודין הוא, ve-din hu,
maybe I could learn it from a קל וחומר, kal va-chomer, or
from an analogy. חייב כאן וחייב באם על הבנים. chayav kan ve-chayav
be-em al ha-banim. You're חייב chayav here and you're חייב chayav by
the mother bird over the children. Again, very analogous, right, mother and
children. מה כשחייב באם על הבנים בנקבה ולא בזכר, mah ke-she-chayav be-em
al ha-banim bi-nekevah ve-lo b-zachar, the same way there it's explicit in
the verse multiple times that we're talking about mother and not father,
אף כשחייב כאן בנקבה ולא בזכר. af ke-she-chayav kan bi-nekevah ve-lo b-zachar.
So there I can learn out from there that that applies to
mothers, this is only applying to mothers just by a very obvious
analogy. Well, maybe I could make that application? אם אמרת באם על
הבנים שכן לא עשה בו מזומן כשאינו מזומן. im amarta be-em al
ha-banim she-kein lo asah bo mezuman ke-she-eino mezuman. There are more leniencies
there. אם, em, the case about the mother over the chicks applies
only by אינו מזומן. eino mezuman. The verse says כי יקרא קן
צפור לפניך, ki yikarei kan tzippor lefanecha, when you chance upon it,
which means that you did not set it aside, it was not
under your control, which by the way, how come in every egg
farm and chicken farm do you not have to start sending away
the roosters? I mean, the hens, right? And the answer is because
it only applies by כי יקרא, ki yikarei, when you chance upon
it, not by מזומן, mezuman, not by something that you are setting
aside and controlling. So there, there are already other leniencies that it
doesn't apply by
מזומן. mezuman. תאמר באותו ואת בנו שעשה בו מזומן כשאינו מזומן? tomar
be-oto ve-et beno she-asah bo mezuman ke-she-eino mezuman? By shechting the mother
and the child, that applies even by animals that are set aside,
even the animals that you're raising. So since there are more stringencies
by shechting, by the shechting of the mother and the child, maybe
it should apply to the father as well. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar
אותו, oto, it, in the singular. אחד ולא שנים, echad ve-lo shenayim,
only one of the two parents. Why didn't it just say שור
או שה ואת בנו shor o seh ve-et beno or something? Why
did it say אותו? oto? Now before we said אותו oto was
to say that you didn't think it meant ox and sheep together.
Fine, now we're ignoring that. We're just saying the word אותו oto
means only one of the parents. אחר שחלק הכתוב, achar she-chillek hakatuv,
once the verse distinguishes and saying only one of the parents, זכיתי
לדין, zachiti la-din, now I can make my comparison. Now that I
know it's not both parents and I have to ask myself which
parent, of course the most obvious parent will be by analogy to
the case of the bird over the chicks and will be the
mother. חייב כאן וחייב באם על הבנים. chayav kan ve-chayav be-em al
ha-banim. Here you're חייב chayav by parents and children and you're חייב
chayav by the mother bird over the children.
מה כשחייב באם על הבנים בנקבה ולא בזכר, mah ke-she-chayav be-em al
ha-banim bi-nekevah ve-lo b-zachar, the
same way there it's explicit about mothers, here too בנקבה ולא בזכר.
bi-nekevah ve-lo b-zachar. It's only mothers and not fathers. So basically the
upshot of the answer is that it's by analogy to the case
of the mother birds over the chicks. The same way there it's
explicit about mothers, here too it's mothers. How do you know it's
not here even a broader and even fathers? That אותו oto tells
us not both parents. But the guide that we have to say
that it means mothers is the analogy to the mother bird over
the chicks.
I understand the לשון. lashon. I understand.
I understand. So then it says ואם נפשך לומר, ve-im nafshecha lomar,
and then if for some reason you're not happy with that answer,
so I'll tell you, בנו, beno, its child, its son or child,
מי שבנו כרוך אחריו. mi she-beno karukh acharayiv.
And this I think gets to the other issues I was talking
about. The one whose child literally entwines himself after her or him
or it or whatever. You know, that is enwrapped with it. The
one that, you know, that has this very intense relationship with its
child. יצא זכר שאין בנו כרוך אחריו. yatza zachar she-ein beno karukh
acharayiv. It's not by the male, although this you know, whether this
is also true by humans, actually there are גמרות Gemaras that say
something like this by humans as well. But at least by animals,
right, there is not this intense relationship with the father as there
is with the mother. So that I think speaks to the issue
that I was saying, which is not just by analogy to the
mother bird over the chicks, but to the idea that in the
animal world the biological relationship, you know, is tru... is, you know,
it dominates and there's really very little of this sort of social
structure of fatherhood that creates a relationship between the father and the
child. So if there's a concern of parent and child in the
animal world, it only makes sense if it is the mother. That's
what I really think is sort of the primary sort of motivating
reason to read the verse out of the simple sense. Let's just
finish this, and then I'll take your questions, Charlie. מאי ואם נפשך
לומר? mai ve-im nafshecha lomar? Why do you have to go to
another reason? Why couldn't you just focus on the comparison to the
mother bird?
וכי תימא, ve-chi teima, because lest you say, אותו זכר משמע. oto
zachar mashma. Thank you very much, right, which is what Michael's been
saying all along. What do you mean? It says in the masculine!
So what are you doing making an analogy to the mother bird
and saying that the masculine here, what Rifka's saying too, all of
a sudden you're ignoring the masculine language, which is completely throughout the
entire
verse? The emphasis of its child and this emphasis that there is
some significant bond between parent and child can only make sense in
the case, certainly in the animal world, in the case of the
mother and not the father.
Because the father and then a male.
No, no, it's not בנו. beno.
In other words, אותו oto is the male and בנו beno is
the male one, meaning that it only applies to a male offspring
with the male parent.
I understand. I understand. The question is how else would it have
said child and not implied... אותה? otah?
No, no, that I know. Let's say it wanted to say child
in a way that does not suggest this intense relationship. How would
you have said that? I have no idea. את הבן et haben
maybe? It seems it's not just the... no, no, it seems it's
the possessive בנו. beno. It's not just it happens to be the
child, it is its child. There's an intense parental relationship. So that
I agree with, it's not a discussion of the simple sense of
the verse, which is completely in the masculine. What I think is
more significant is that it reflects the גמרא's Gemara quite explicit here
what is motivating it. Number one, a comparison to a similar מצוה
mitzvah and more I would say what dominates, and that's exactly what
the גמרא Gemara says, that might not have trumped the simple grammar
of the verse, which is very clearly masculine. But the point is
if there's a concern here about a family unit and a relationship
between a parent and a child in the animal world, the גמרא
Gemara could not have... חז"ל Chazal could not have understood that that
would have had carried any weight in the sense of father and
child. Let's read one more sentence and then Charlie has a question
and then that will end. Okay. יצא זכר שאין בנו כרוך אחריו,
yatza zachar she-ein beno karuch acharav, which does not apply to the
male. Let's go to top of ע"ח ע"ב. ayin chet amud bet.
ולחנניא, u'le-Chananya, and what does חנניא Chananya say, who says that it
applies to female and male? Top of ע"ח ע"ב. ayin chet amud
bet. כתיב אותו ketiv oto דמשמע זכר. d'mashma zachar.
It says it, or him, which is in the masculine, which is
the father. וכתיב בנו, u'chetiv beno, which is again I think the
possessive, its child, a sense of a real intense parent-child relationship. מי
שבנו כרוך אחריו, mi she-beno karuch acharav,
which means an intense parent-child relationship דמשמע נקבה. d'mashma nekeiva.
So the use of the
masculine suggests we're also talking about the father. The fact that it
speaks about this, its child and this intense relationship, that indicates the
mother. הילכך נוהג בין בזכרים בין בנקבות. hilkach noheg bein bi-zcharim bein
bi-nekeivot. Therefore it applies both to mothers and to fathers. Okay, so
here's a really fascinating case where based on certain assumptions about that
obviously the תורה's Torah concern is about a sense of a family
unit here, חז"ל Chazal read to interpret the verse to completely sort
of dismiss the use of the masculine. Charlie, you had a question.
Yeah, there's a practical thing. If you require that... if you hold
by חנניא Chananya and it applies to the fathers as well, you've
got a practical matter. You're almost never going to be able to
slaughter anything because unless you have only one male animal in your
herd, you are never going to
know who the father is. Okay, so that's another question, which is
even if it does apply to fathers, if you don't know who
the father is, how much do you have to worry about it?
Okay, that's a second-degree question. First we have to determine if it
applies to fathers, then we have to worry about what if you
can't figure that out. Okay, מרדכי, Mordechai, you had a question? Okay,
everyone, we'll continue tomorrow. בנו... beno... could you say בנו beno and
not בנינו? beneinu?